welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right check-ins I'm five percent
nervous and then 95% full of Lumos
because James Carr says here at the
store so welcome to the store the stoah
is a place for us to cohere and dialogue
about what matters most at the nice edge
of this moment and I'm Peter Lindberg
the Stewart of the store and for those
of you who may be new to the store maybe
I'll just give a brief introduction to
it because we have a lot of new faces I
see I'm dealing the stoah as not a place
to talk about stoicism but a place
that's stewarded by a stoic myself and
for us to talk about what's most
important during this meta crisis and we
have few type types of events we have
these sense-making series and these kind
of one-off events where people come in
and share their thoughts and then we
source the collective intelligence for
questions and then we have a wisdom gym
that's forming right now where there's
like an ecology of practices of
different sessions to help us build our
sovereignty and coherence during this
mist meta-crisis and today we have James
cars' so this man probably needs no
introduction amongst this audience but
he's a professor emeritus of history and
literature of religion at New York
University he's the author of numerous
books one of them being the religious
case against belief and finite and
infinite games legendary book and he's a
legend in this wider sense making space
that a lot of us belong to so what's
gonna happen today is James is gonna
share his thoughts on how to play the
infinite game during this crisis or meta
crisis that we find ourselves in I will
follow up with a few questions about you
know his latest book that he's writing
and if you have any questions for James
pop them in the chat box I will call on
you you unmute yourself and then you ask
your question if you want me to read
your question on your behalf I will do
so this will be recorded on YouTube so
just keep that in mind and there would
be recorded and posted on YouTube I
should say
and what else should I say oh yeah keep
yourself off like on mute I should say I
don't need your self unless you're
you're gonna ask a question so that
being said Oh James how do we play the
infinite game during the Semitic crisis
we find ourselves in you know the crisis
is like nothing of course I've seen in
my lifetime but you know at the same
time it's a it's a terrible crisis
there's there's not an easy exit to this
one but at the same time it gives us
it's the crisis is almost tailor-made
for a kind of reasonable attitude toward
the future our thinking about what's
what's coming down ahead of us I mean
right now everyone is thinking in future
in terms that we could call future all
that is that is to say looking back at
where we are now from some kind of
imagined place out there which may or
may not be one a place we want to go to
so so is very it's a very good time to
do some thinking about some long-range
thinking and that's that's what I what
I've been doing I've been thinking a lot
about the way we engage each other in
all kinds of social relations of course
the political the whole political world
is in turmoil we have to do some very
careful thinking about that and so I can
I can discuss any of these issues with
you anything that is of immediate
importance to you or significance yeah I
have a few but I wonder what's most
alive for you when you when you're
thinking about this current situation
and what's most alive for me is I is to
think that there's got to be we have to
make our way to a more civilized place
we're in a kind of civilization but it's
in it's also in Christ
and so I'm looking for ways to make
ourselves more civilized and so those
are those that means addressing some
very big issues for example racial
discrimination that's one of course a
very big one very important another one
is the the use of the environment the
use of our land and in both cases it's
very painful because as Americans as
being the nation we are we have not done
a good job with either of those
categories in the first place we're
living on stolen land this land really
belongs to but you know it's very very
funny thing when America's best food
cheap I came to the new world he he
actually used the term new world he came
right after Columbus was here and we
have his we borrowed his name his first
name Amerigo for the the word American
but when he came he was he was not
looking for a new world he was trying to
bring the old world with him and what I
would like to do is look forward in a
way that looks toward a new world a lot
of new categories and so on a lot of new
ways to approach things I mean even for
something as simple as schooling or
education in the large sense I mean I
could talk about that at length but but
that that's now becomes very very
important most important for me now even
though a lot of the future is being
thought about in technological terms or
in mechanical terms and so on I think
what we need is an intellectual
revolution not so much a revolution of
engineering or technology we've got
enough of that so I'm thinking in those
kind of those categories yeah I have to
double-click on the intellectual
revolution because that speaks to me and
a lot of us here at the stove can you
speak more on that what do you mean by
an intellectual revolution well I mean
rethinking what we do I
I I I'm as you know from reading my book
I'm heavily influenced by the Greek
philosophers
I'm also heavily influenced by the the
Hebrew tradition the Jews the Jewish
tradition especially the rabbinical
tradition those two combined are
fascinating in the following way
that once you get into a deep discussion
the self-examination what the Greeks
called dialectic and what the the Jews
call Talmud the conversation itself
begins to convert to community and
becomes a kind of it becomes a people I
mean we saw this happen within in the
Jewish tradition over the 2,000 years
since they had the destruction of the
Temple in Jerusalem they became a people
by by way of conversation with each
other it's quite quite remarkable
and so what I want to do is get into
that kind of deep conversation about the
future deep enough that it creates
community as well as intellectual
clarity and I know as a you're leaning
toward the Stoics of course they had
similar similar attitude but but
basically I consider myself shall we say
a dialectical thinker that as I want to
I want to question where we are
look look deeply into it and then see
where we can go from here yes yes that
resonates a lot that's sort of like our
Jam here at the stoah do you see any
communities that are embodying this
right now well you know I don't much
I'll tell you one thing I'm very
disappointed in the I'll give you a
little history just a little bit of
history so so Plato in 400 years in 400
BC roughly found in the Academy he
bought up he born
an olive grove and decided to meet
students there and established an
academy well the Academy lasted seventy
seven hundred and fifty years quite an
extraordinary run and there it began not
only stoicism but also all kinds of
other movements different different you
know different varieties of Neoplatonism
and Platonism aristotelianism and so on
and Aristotle himself had a school that
lasted for for a long time but but and
that school then became over time a
model for the University now the
university in in the it was was really
kind of conceived roughly in the in the
Platonic mode that is to say a group of
people getting together talking deeply
with each other over issues that should
be of concern to the entire community
well the what happens happened over time
is that the the university the modern
university has become more and more
expensive to operate and therefore in a
kind of quest for money they've allowed
themselves to be influenced by outside
money and in some ways that that
actually that that money now is
determining what we know is choosing
what research scientists are yeah you
know another they're making up the
knowledge we're going to have whereas
for Plato in that in that August
classical tradition you didn't have an
idea ahead of what you're going to find
you you went out on a free search to see
what was there what you could what you
could find but but this is not the case
on the modern University and I'm very
upset about it I think that what's
happened is that a lot of faculty have
sold themselves to moneyed supporters
and it's it's a kind of selling out of
the university itself
yeah so one thing we talk about here is
like thinking in public and how
difficult it is so I'm curious in order
for this intellectual revolution to
emerge what do you think are the
barriers that need to be removed and
what do you think are the conditions
that need to be in place for it to
happen well I think the first thing we
do is open the university right now
we're stuck in a kind of meritocratic
situation where people where
universities are now selecting students
because they can grade highly on certain
tests and so on and this create this
I mean it's complicated to explain but
the meritocracy is attempting to create
a kind of permanent upper class of
financial a financial class and it's
it's terrifically unfair so I've been
thinking about ways of counteracting the
meritocracy in one way just to give you
a shocking idea of some of the stuff
that's in my head I would like to to
professionalize student students not
give them scholarships hire them to be
students and and break up universities
into intellectual centers rather than
the four-year march through you know the
the 8th semester program which by the
way is completely arbitrary anyway that
was never a part of the university
system when it was founded back in the
12th century so so the the what I would
like to see is it's a whole new kind of
approach to teaching where we spend a
lot of money on education now now people
are going to save right away well that's
where do we get that money well by the
way we are spending over a trillion
dollars every year those Americans are
on the military and if we can pay that
much
two people to go to war we can pay that
much two people to go to school so but
when I'm what I'm proposing is a really
big shift in the way we think about our
money we think about our future we think
about our education and we think about
the coming crisis which is actually I
mean the the current crisis is bad
enough but the coming crisis is the
really bad one that environmental crisis
so anyway that's the way my thinking is
doing this for example that's one at one
example of it yeah I love it get you
another example yeah I would say one of
the things we have to start thinking
about it's an alternative to Ottoman to
the automobile and if you if you think
about it the automobile has now been
available commercially for a hundred and
fifty years and about an era now I don't
mean just automobiles I mean the whole
way of moving ourselves around
transporting ourselves has been around
including airplanes beginning in 1903
with the first flight in in Kitty Hawk
and then I mean it's okay it's amazing
Peter in a way when you think about it
you see how fast this technology's
developed in 1903 well it sort of in the
middle of the nineteenth century they
began doing the the internal combustion
engine and and began selling it
commercially then 1903 50 years later
basically we got off the off the ground
into the sky and then only 66 years
later we got a gun we get people on the
moon which you know that's that's really
very rapid technology but we have we
have to consider a bit won't look more
deeply into that because in the meantime
although then the internal combustion
engine has gone far to make our planet
habitable it's also gone very far to
make it uninhabitable
in fact if we keep building cars and
designing them the way we do will will
actually
and and and our race as it sounds I mean
it's we are in a dire situation looking
looking toward the end of the of the
century I I just see this this kind of
wall coming down at us and we've got to
start thinking creatively about it and
one of the ways is to wreak conceived
the automobile right so I have a few
questions and then we're gonna pivot to
the room and the title of this talk is
playing the infinite game during
meta-crisis and I don't know if you're
familiar with that concept but I think I
described it to you somewhat in the
email is like there's an ecology of
crises that we have like there racial
discrimination the environments you name
it and in that people are overwhelmed by
by all this and overwhelmed by what's
happening and and there's like a
uncertainty of what to do of how they
can be deployed to making the world a
better place and so I guess the broad
question for you is how do we infinite
infinitely play during this meta crisis
[Laughter]
about what our issues are our dreams and
so on and we we look at the ways in
which we compete with each other we look
at the ways in which we spend money with
each other and so on and nothing is is
really off limits and these discussions
they can be psychological they can be
political sociological and so on but
we've got to do that we've got to sit
down and talk with each other I mean for
example think about the way we look at
our vocations number but most of us see
most of us pin our identity on the kind
of employment of the job or the
profession we have I think that's a
mistake I think we ought to think of
ourselves as thinkers primarily and then
in gay and people who are in gay
our professions or vocations and that
that will mean for a lot of people
especially now in the current crisis
giving up comfortable positions they
hold jobs that they're in now that may
or may not pay that probably pay pretty
well but but may not and therefore think
about living in a way that can extend
that that wealth out of you
ahead of yourself I mean that that's in
a way that's abstract invade but but I
think when we when we when we get
together and talk about real issues we
can start doing that I mean we could
start with with race with distribution
with the with the way cities are
organized with the way we've developed
suburbs with the way we have taken the
heart out of cities but I'm going to
look at the ways in which we create art
what I mean our do we want museums to
operate the way they do or do we want
them right now a museum is a place where
art ends up I want to see it as a place
where art starts off I'm gonna see
museums convert to schools to training
centers and so on among other things I
mean that's what I'm gonna see jails
treated like school it's not like not
like like for wall prisons but put a
jail in a in a in a campus and and have
and have really qualified talented
teachers and so on so honor codes and
there's there's a lot of thinkers like I
guess pair academic thinkers that are
converging on what you just talked about
this idea that we need dialogue like
real dialogue or some logos and it what
what is that like again the conditions
of the intellectual revolution needs to
occur but what are the conditions of
like genuine dialogue well the the first
thing is we need someone you have to
start
I mean I'm again using the classical
model and the
all died actually Plato remember
invented dialogue and and invented what
he called yeah I mean of course the the
Greek word is dialectic a dialect
dialect and what what he meant by it was
someone challenging one person
challenging another are beginning to ask
what is it you know how well do you know
it and here's what I think about what
you know and then the other person
answers and so on and they keep going on
on this exchange and it's a kind of and
in a way it's a challenge in a way it's
a it's a denial it's a way of saying to
each other I don't think you're quite
right about that we want to look more
deeply into it but but also it's it's a
kind of discourse it has no end
I mean if you read for example if you
read the Platonic dialogues they never
come out with a conclusion and and
Aristotle himself even though he took a
lot of very famous views on different
subjects subjects he he always hesitated
to come down and fixed on anything and I
think that too is a model keep our minds
open I mean I can go on about this but
yeah I like that so we're gonna turn our
attention to the chat in a moment the
last question you got a book you're
writing or is coming out can you speak a
little bit more on that
oh yes I've written a book I call the
poetry of money the poetry of money and
what I mean by that I'm taking again the
word poetry from the classics places I
actually wrote some about something
about that in the games book I wrote a
little bit of a summary of what the
Greeks meant by places which is poetry
they meant by it the the creation of
something absolutely new they didn't
they didn't mean only verse I mean they
meant that too but
but mainly it was kind of someone
engaged in creative work would start
something and not know exactly where
they're going to end to take off with
without any borders or limits or
necessary requirements and so on and see
where it were developed they put this in
opposition to what they called techno
which which we translate as craft or
artisanship that's something like that
so techno techno and poesis are two
different things all together and when
we when we use a technique or technique
with money mainly what we're trying to
do is make it it is develop riches out
of what I call Richards whereas to be
something creative with money is not
only to and enlarge the money but to to
enlarge in such a way that it creates
possibilities out ahead of itself the
model would be Plato's Academy he paid
cash for it he came he paid gold gold
coins stamped gold coins and bought this
this olive grove I'm sure it paid off a
little but that's not yeah the idea was
not to make money from olives the idea
was to engage in this course with people
and that was a payoff that that
investment paid off like nothing else
750 years with that heavy intellectual
contribution really shaped thinking of
the entire western world I mean an
awesome contribution so I'm thinking of
trying to find ways of using money
spending money that have that creative
outcome if we use money to to to produce
to get more money to add to our riches
that that actually doesn't work well in
a society it tends to create classes it
tends to distort politics and and does a
lot of damage to the economy so I I want
to try
revision of our thinking about the way
we use money I dig it man I dig it so
just before I ask a choir calling
someone from the chat to ask a question
someone said cars for president 2020 is
that is that a possibility no okay
so I'm gonna turn to the questions now
when I call on you and meet yourself
unless you want me to read on your
behalf again this is going to go on
YouTube please be concise with your
question and yeah so let's do point I
won't be able to read all the questions
obviously and it won't be in the order
so just FYI fan don't get to your
question so Moritz you had a question
you're gonna be yourself so my question
is how do you deal with groups that are
playing finite games and that are not
interested in playing infinite games
oh no I know it's what you have to you
have to find ways to talk to people I
mean they actually what they want you to
do what a group is playing when a group
is playing a finite game and and wants
to finish that game and so on there
they're very unlikely to ask anyone to
join them it's an exclusive operation so
what you want to do is hang around them
stay with them learn their language and
find ways of talking with them outside
the game now when when some of the I had
an experience when I was a kid I'll go
through very quickly we we played we had
a little I was living in Chicago at the
time and there were a couple vacant lots
near us we played a softball game there
every day actually just played softball
the game went all day long come and
people come and go and so on every once
in a while a few brutes would come by
and they'd want to break up the game
they want to win the game you know they
want to get in there but there was a guy
who became a model for me in my in my
life a little guy named John filling him
he was probably the smallest guy in that
whole outfit among my friends
whose - who who started giving these
intruders these these kind of brutish
guys nicknames hey champ speed you know
he gave him all kinds of names like that
and then got them into the game by way
of their of their of their label they
titled their you know their nickname and
and they began to love it and so on
because he found a way of getting into
their discourse and that's the only way
you're going to do this you're not going
to you're not going to settle it by
winning their game that will not impress
them not at all they'll just want to
play again you know fight again and so
on
no you have to find a way of of talking
with them that is part of their their
vernacular part of their their their
dialectic within themselves part of
their their rhetoric with each other
that's the best I can do on that one
good luck great
Nicholas Benjamin you had a question
here I did thank you so much for writing
this book for doing all of that research
on that note it's with perfect hindsight
given what you know about the world now
where we are now and where we're headed
you can rewrite finite an evening game
editor for the first time which I'm
which topic well I
one thing I didn't talk about it all in
the in the games book is money you know
economics and so on I talk a lot of it
it has a kind of political caste if you
if you think about it what am I one of
the points I want to make in the book
although it's a small it makes get a
small point it's a big point in my head
and that is we should all be political
but not have a politics that's what
that's what gets us in trouble having a
very fixed idea of what our society
should be and then trying to go do that
that's a mistake
that's what that was that's what I
learned from from years of reading marks
to marks had a very specific idea about
about the way he wanted to go and it was
too specific yeah in the end he foiled
himself he can't fell into contradiction
himself and one of the things I would I
would like to do is to look more closely
at the way we spend money the way we use
our resources are finite resources and
in a kind of material way I didn't do
that so much in the games but I'm trying
that now with a new book but at least
that's that's what I wish I had done
probably one more thing I wish I had
stressed the importance of evil a little
bit more because I think we have in our
sense well in the 20th century
remember we killed over 200 million
people by government action I mean this
this is extraordinary that's not that's
evil but anyone's definition so we need
we need to read rethink some of that too
yeah
thank you it's some some delicious
questions today re oh you have a you
have a question yeah so hello thank you
so much for this yeah yeah so you seem
pretty critical of our societies like
intensely competitive culture I was
wondering if you see any role for
competition in the intellectual
revolution to come and if so what it
might look like oh thank you that's a
good question yes I do I I think we are
inherently competitive
I think we're born competitive actually
just let me give you a little bit of
history on that James the name the
author of Hobbes author of the great
book Leviathan that he wrote in the
seven and near the end of the 17th
century
well Hobbes Hobbes made the point that I
was not born
hello oh yeah it's okay someone just
went off you dick Hobbs made the point
that if I still talking to ya I really
the point that we are born competitive
and as soon as we come out of the womb
we're grabbing for things said we want
that stuff we want that one with this
one and so he invented a figure called
the Leviathan that that rules over
society and keeps people from from
attacking each other eating each other
up and so on he's trying to prevent what
he called the war of war again the war
of all wars were there where we go into
battle with each other and and everyone
loses but but he had a point which i
think is very important competition
comes with being human so a lot of the
things we desire we desire them not
because there's a shortage of them but
because we're competitive for them and
so I think one thing we do is look at
the kinds of things we want out of our
life and try to peg that to our own
natural competition do we want it
because it will make us a little bit
better a little higher a little farther
out than someone else or do we want it
because it's a it's a it's a it's my own
desire period that's that's a different
way of different level of consciousness
so yeah I think we remain competitive
that's fine I I like competition
competition you know there are two
things that happen when a baby is born
either it's very we're born with two
kind of contrary instincts the one is to
be competitive in a warrior sense and
the other is to be competitive in a
playful sense and and I think the the
warrior at times dominates in the player
at times dominates and so we want to
remember that the player is interested
in keeping the country keeping a
competition going whereas the warrior
wants to
wants to end it in his or her favor so
so look at yourself that way is that
kind of a finite player if it's
something you want if what you're doing
is supporting emphasizing and
reinforcing the competitive character of
human nature then you're fine if what
you want to shut people up and make them
do what you want them to do not what
they want to do that's not so good on
John you had a question they think
thanks James I'm gonna read out my
question yeah what do you feel people
most misunderstand misconstrue about the
concept of infinite and finite games and
to ask a slight follow-up what aspects
of the framework do you think are
overhyped which aspects do you feel are
underhyped yeah I can answer that the a
lot of people read the notion a lot of
people when they first hear the term
infinite tend to think something very
large happening for them or to them I
I've been struck by the number of
business people who've who've written me
with interest about the infinite game I
think for some of them they have a kind
of fantasy of an infinite income you
know of multiplying their income many
times but that's not really what I have
in mind what I have in mind is it's a
consecutive is a series of engagements
with each other in which a number of
things happen for one thing it builds
community we once those who play
together stay together and use a really
corny term but but I think that's true
and and so the kind of verbal dialogue
we have with each other the kind of
competition over anything we have with
each other as long as we are affirming
our competitive spirit
then we're we're I think on our way to
what I would call infinite play but but
the distortion comes when people think
that they're going to be the recipient
of something very large very you know
sort of very big infinite thing out
there well say our riches that's that I
think is one of the ways in which is
it's distorted great Dan Feldman he had
a question yes James I have a question
for you um how does reclaiming the
Commons relate to infinite games if at
all say a little more about that we can
good well right now we have essentially
the state and the market and the mark
and it's basically a state that's been
captured by the market and in the last
at least the last 50 years and probably
last since the dawn of the Industrial
Revolution maybe back to log enclosures
and stuff we got rid of we got rid of
the Acamas since then under the forests
and so on and so forth oh I'll
reclaiming comments in that sense yeah
oh I'm very much before that the I think
what happened is what's happened
economically in the last and politically
of course at the same time in the last
several centuries I go back to Adam
Smith on this one Smith as you know had
the idea of an invisible hand where the
market operated on its own by itself it
was a kind of a it's interesting Smith
wrote at the beginning of the mechanic
of the Industrial Age and so therefore
he had a mechanistic notion of the of
the market in fact it was only a couple
years after he published his his great
book for Wealth of Nations when this guy
this poor guy Lud tried to destroy a
machine and in England so I mean it came
in that and
and that kind of spirit but that that
notion of a mechanism of a market
mechanism still dominates today so a lot
of people think that the market is out
there doing its thing when as a matter
of fact we are deciding what the market
is the market is not something as doing
it doing to us it's what we're doing to
ourselves basically and so we've got
we've got to take back the notion that
the market is a function of our
imagination not a function of not a
function of money or politics or
anything else because that too is a
function of our imagination so so we
have to do some very deep thinking about
how we got here and how we're going to
get out and I I see ways of getting out
I'm trying to articulate some of those
myself and in this book I've written so
thanks thanks from that but I I want
that comments back Thank You Manuel you
had a question about sexuality I believe
if you can unmute yourself I was hoping
for some comments please on infinite
sexuality in our current context I
believe the quote was that the only true
revolution is the restoration of genius
to sexuality so I wonder how thoughts
might flush out in this time well for
one thing the term genius I take very
seriously genius is not it's not
necessarily an ability it is it is
working from the center of your of your
consciousness of your of your life
so anything you do from your G you know
an act of genius is a genuine act I
think that's probably the best way to
look
so try to find that that's this is very
hard to do try to find in yourself what
you consider for yourself to be a
genuine act if you if you're if it's out
of your your personal Center which is
unlike absolutely unlike anyone elses
can't be categorized doesn't belong to
any sort of type or sexual identity it's
just it's you you know deep down then
once you find that and you you act from
that act it's what I call original
acting or ingenious acting where we
where we remove from from ourselves
outward now but the world doesn't always
like the way we move from ourselves
outward so so conflicts develop and
that's that's that's I think where most
of the issues lie it's not not being
honest with ourselves but being honest
with the world and taking what the world
gives us in response which is often
negative and critical and sometimes
hurtful if not violent so so you it
becomes very delicate the farther out
you got you the closer you are to
yourself the more expressive you can be
but the farther out you have to be a
little a little more careful
no not I'm not telling you to stop I'm
just saying
prepare yourself to be defined not
always so a welcome audience out there
people who wish there are a lot of
people who don't want you to be who you
are because of the fens them in one way
or another and so that's something
you've got to start with a recognition
you have to start with but start but go
there anyway love it
Jessica Watson Miller you had a question
earlier yeah I'm just wondering if you
could speak a bit about authoritarianism
or finite game meanness of
authoritarianism and maybe about how
that relates to the current situation
that we're in
yeah well what we see is people who want
to be winners and the it's interesting
how yeah you know if you if you read
history a little bit like I do one of
them one of the great conflicts you see
all the way from the from the time of
the Greeks for the present actually
probably the same in Asia is on the one
hand you you have powerful figures who
want the world to be a certain way then
you've got creative people under them or
around them who threatened them now it's
it's a very strange thing to me that
that a poet would be more dangerous to a
tyrant than another army and so if you
look if you if you read history
carefully you'll find that poets are
often poets journalists writers authors
creators are all kinds of people are
often exiled and and they're very
upsetting to the to the rulers so what
we have now is an anti poetic leadership
authoritarianism there and there were
lots of ways to look at it if you don't
mind by being political than better a
number one we see very little sense of
humor in our leadership a number two not
any of them not Trump not Xi Jinping not
not bohlson ro and Brazil not you know
this one that one knew and so on
not not anyway not any of them are
themselves artists or poets they create
nothing they've given us nothing to live
by no quotes to live by and so on so
they are poetically starved and I think
that's what clinically deprived deprave
to but but mostly deprived that's that's
my view of authoritarianism it's a it's
a dread of poetry
it's a dread of creativity
and and there there they are they mean
business about it
Trump is terrified by free thinkers cool
that answer
Jeff Loveland your question you can
unmute yourself Jeff
okay maybe I'll find someone else did it
Susan did you have a question yes so
it's an honor to to be able to
participate thank you for being here mr.
Carson um so I'm kind of wandering
around a what are the mental models that
that have got to shift to you to move
the dial you kind of alluded to winning
and I picked up on that win lose but is
there what what is it that is that he's
got to be that shift that you know we've
got to get the the people to play to
play the infinite game to make that
attractive no it's very hard to do but
but I think we can do it by actually let
me put it this way sis and I think we
have to do it I think we don't we're in
very big trouble
so I mean really big trouble so one of
the things I think we need is it's a
kind of gap we need people working with
each other talking with each other about
problems and whatever those problems are
we begin we begin relatively small but
but this those conversations become can
become quite large I would I would like
to I think I'd like to find ways to to
encourage the creativity the originality
of people of freeing themselves from any
kind of strict ideology I made that one
of the things we have today that
everyone's talking about
is this very sharp division between the
rights and left the end the out up and
down and so on the rich and the poor
the black and the white these conflicts
are terrible but I think we have to
engage find ways of addressing all of
them creatively because you if I were to
say why would we want to talk about
problems because problems are really
finite why are we would you say that
maybe the the pathway would be to
reframe the conversation about yeah
that's right you start with the problem
but you transform it pretty quickly
that's that's why I like the notion of
speaking dialectically that is you you
get in a situation say wait a minute
I mean if you if you follow like Plato's
dialogues Plato Socrates was always able
to change the subject and you know that
if you start off talking about justice
then you're suddenly you're talking
about you know at one point in the
dialogue the theaetetus Socrates stops
this young mathematician and says what
kind of what do you what do you call
knowledge and the guy gives some lines
and some examples and next thing over
we're talking about the nature of the
state the sold knowledge wisdom and so
on it just went on in a very different
direction so we have to keep an open
mind in our discussions stop trying to
get people to think a certain way stop
as I said a little earlier instead of be
political but they don't have the
politics and that in that sense don't
have a try to be ideologically free
that's what that's my best shot at that
cool cool maybe gray you had a
questioners table yeah I I've been
really curious especially with all of
the sort of polarizing discourse around
the meta crisis and the pandemic about
how you would relate that to what you
about in the religious case against
belief around how communitas is
something that comes out of the polettis
ISM that is like so like rooted out by
the structure of our political system
right now oh yeah yeah very good
okay yes right what we have and I made
the distinction thank you for that
I made the distinction in that book
between the community Oz and Civitas if
you remember right
and and Civitas is a society thought of
top top down whereas communitas is the
society thinking about itself from the
bottom up so it's a neighborhood is a
community the city government is a
Civitas and so on but Civitas involves a
lot more it involves it a whole lot of
social mores you know except in public
behavior of unwritten laws and and so on
whereas communitas doesn't have a fixed
content it has a certain style though of
originality and creativity so the you
know to pick up when I said a little bit
earlier of what a lot of political
leaders are afraid of is the communities
they're not they're not afraid of
another Civitas as much as they are
rival Civitas as much as they are the
communities underneath them I mean the
worst thing you can do to a dictator is
laugh at the dictator and you know that
that's why it's very interesting that
Trump doesn't have a sense of humor he
can't laugh he definitely can't laugh at
himself but also can't have anyone else
laugh at him he's very very delicate
about that so so great leaders are
people who who expect to be laughed at
Roosevelt said the bankers are scorning
me haha I love it you know and so on so
so we we need we need an attitude toward
community to us like that it can be very
refreshing and very liberating and very
Reforma thanks for the question
thank you so much Anton you're a
question above about money if you would
unmute yourself and ask that yeah Thank
You Victor yeah thank you all so it's
James for this so much of this is
resonating I had a question in James
about about economics you're talking
about economics earlier we thought you
thought you talking about money and my
question was do you think we can play
infinite games without current form of
money or can we at least expand the
nature of the games that we play with
our current form of money and or do we
need do we need new form of new forms of
money in the forms of economics in order
to really create infinite games how much
can we do with our current form of
linear in economics yeah well I don't
think we need a new form of money I
think we need a new attitude toward
money now I I make a distinction you
know it's it's it's hard to carry this
off and I'm making a distinction between
being rich and being wealthy now to be
rich is to add to the amount of dollars
you have or whatever your currency is
and you that's something you can count
it belongs only to you its individual
and no one else has a legal right to it
but you
whereas wealth I take is a completely
different thing the I I want to go back
to the word itself wealth wheel meaning
the well-being of a situation or a
country or a person or a community and
and so one way of spending money is for
the well-being of a community and and
one of the very most effective ways of
doing that is education spending money
on schools that's those are really great
investments those investments pay off
whereas if you invest just to get richer
that really kind of shuts the money down
that's the flow down and nothing really
much comes of it that's why if we if we
look at the at the money classes of very
rich people we find very little going on
that's original creative artistic lovely
and so on I mean I look at a museum with
with big names on it as a kind of a
testimony of those people that this is
something they can't do they've they're
hiring artists to sort of an oval their
name well that's it that's that's a
terrible use of money why don't they
give that money to a school and and
develop artists allow artists to grow
out of and so on I I think I think there
are ways of using money that are that
are creative hopeful and will end in
communities well-being yeah can I just
add one thing my concern with money is
basically that the medium of exchange is
the message so if you up do something to
Marshall McLuhan there and our whole
society our whole culture is built
around the money system and it's created
by the powers that be and so I just
wonder if we can ever really play in
connect games with it so I think money
creation is such a central aspect to to
whether we are in a finite or an
infinite game no I I'm all in favor of
the kind of investment that will lead to
investments rather than the kind of
investment that will lead to someone's
riches and and what that usually means
is a communal expense that is to say a
focus on the way communities are
organized and what they're doing and and
and and giving a lot of freedom to
different organizations and so on I mean
one of the few heard my
branch about the university where right
now wealth riches rather are really
controlling what what the universities
are doing and that's that's it that's a
grave mistake that's a very bad
investment on society's part they should
be endowing universities paying for
scholarships for all kinds of people no
no everybody you know even even
prisoners I want I want to be in schools
of Education American various kinds and
all because all of that in the end pays
off it pays off in a way that investing
in their in the what we call usually
call the market doesn't it doesn't pay
off I mean I got this is a big big
question but a big subject but that
that's roughly the way I go on answering
it great James you have time for one
more question sure
Joe if you had a question if you're
gonna meet yourself sure greetings from
Berlin in a fan of your book for many
years I think I've probably bought 10
copies and given you my question many
people are playing finite games either
because they're in fairly desperate
conditions or they imagine that they are
in desperate conditions for various
psychological reasons what needs to
happen for these people to start playing
infinite games oh that's that's that's
hard I know I know exactly what you mean
I I mean I I grew up I was a kind of I
mean well I was very athletic when I was
young I actually paid my way through
college I sort of regret to say but it
did and and I think one of the reasons I
wrote the book is that my experience
being an athlete a very competitive
athlete was not pleasant it was if there
was something about it that I really
didn't like and it was it was full of
all kinds of tensions and
psychological tricks and so on that it
just didn't ring ring true to me so it
took me a long time to sort of break out
of that to free myself from that that
very rigid conception of a finite game I
think I think the only way to do it is
not to it's not to come head to head
with other finite players you don't want
to be a finite player trying to edify it
a finite game you know you you you want
somehow to pick up as I said a little
earlier pick up their rhetoric the way
they think the way they talk with each
other their vocabulary their conceptual
the way they conceptualize things and
and begin talking that way but that's
I'm not easy that's hard and you sort of
have to come at it as maybe a companion
or a co player yourself and so on but
but it's the only way of going about a
direct encounter won't work it may work
but it probably won't anymore and hey
you hungry for a couple more change
weekend yeah okay we just got one from a
cow if you want to reach your question
yes thank you James Peter sorry so as we
know in our democratic system
you know election needs to win election
they have finished terms and the terms
are you know short windows in the grand
scheme of things how can we make sure
that the magnetic system are played with
players with infant mindset oh I don't I
think the only way to do it is somewhat
indirectly that is to say create a kind
of what I would what I call in other
books a Humanitas namely our community
eyes rather
we're where we have a broad shared
notion of what fair competition is
that's very very hard to develop you
know in a large country like Canada or
the United States but but it is possible
you have to prepare the in other words
the the persons who need most to be
corrected are not the politicians
they're the people who choose the
politicians so so that's where you start
you start at the bottom and you you go
to people you talk to people and in
their language their their discourse
their their dialogue their their
dielectric and so on and and and and
work up that way rather than then try to
pick out somebody who's going to do it
for you from the top down but those are
movements very difficult to develop
we're seeing that we're seeing the
beginnings of it right now in the after
the the covin crisis we're seeing and
you know in the racial issue right now
in America especially a beginning we see
a movement beginning that's going to
have I'm quite sure profound effect on
the on the upper structure on the on the
leadership structure of the society so
we should we should look for that but
that's where we go we go from the bottom
up not the top down cool happy you had a
question yeah hi Jim um my question is
about are there times where it's
necessary to play the finite game within
the infinite game sure oh yeah yeah
funny games can be wonderful the key
though is what you're doing when you
play the finite game if if if you are
truly putting yourself ahead of someone
you know go back to the notion between
the warrior and the play the player the
warrior wants to end the
test in his or her favor and whereas the
player wants to end the contest but then
it's ready for another you know another
level of play and that's the important
thing
it's long as you you don't want to bring
the thing to a definitive end then
you're more on the side of an infinite
player than you are a finite player and
there are a lot of finite games
interfund that are fun to play I mean I
think even a profession or a sports
event or something like that
I can qualify as a perfectly legitimate
wonderful in fact even sort of
beneficial find out game great Jeff
Loveland I think you're back if you can
ask your question yes thanks Peter
thank you mister cars how do we
cultivate discernment and identifying
people who talked the infinite game talk
but don't walk the infinite game so
those are the people I know a lot of the
people I know don't want to lose
anything you know they they want always
to be some on the winning side so I and
I know a lot of examples in my life of
people who you know will well just take
a really simple example I I placed a lot
of squash in my younger years obviously
but but I I remember being really brutal
on them on the court you know hitting
that ball like you know just like I
wanted to kill the ball and my opponent
and then going out for a cafe latte you
know afterwards and so on laughing and
even forgetting who won the game but it
was great fun playing it but but it's
tricky at the beginning you you're not
you can't you you you have to you have
to make a judgment some people don't
want to some people just want to win I
mean there are people in that this is
when I was still teaching it and while
you we had a big the kind of a bunch of
squash courts and there was a crowd that
played and there were there were people
in that crowd who really didn't want to
lose and and you had to avoid them I
mean they were they were not they're
really not fun to play with or not in
particularly good to play with either
and even when I beat them upset but
usually I lost anyway thanks for the
question so here's a question maybe this
will be the question we end off with I
don't know if there's any more will come
in but here is one that I was asked to
read ok do you have any suggestions for
regular daily religious mindfulness
practices can you discuss any daily
practice that you have I don't I don't
have I don't have what you could call a
discipline you know a yoga or any sort
of chanting or the material activities
so on but I do have I try to maintain an
attitude of always looking for where the
mystery is no matter what the issue is
what is mysterious about this
particularly even a very plain event you
want to look at it and say no wait a
minute that doesn't explain everything
there's something going on here I don't
get what could that possibly be and they
kind of focus on that and that's that
would be my my the simplest answer I
have to that and that but that comes
after years and years and years of of
reading a lot of religious texts having
a lot of exposure to different kinds of
religious disciplines and never quite
being taken up by any of
but but having an attitude of well you
know maybe for all of them right so
maybe I'll close off with a question we
last chat when he came on the podcast we
talked about this term the metagame that
a lot of people that everyone geeks out
about meta nowadays it's like the word
that people love to use yeah and then
the idea of the meta game like there's
an ecology of games of finite if in the
games and then being able to go above
them and have a look at them and then
you know figure out which one to play
from that you find that a useful comment
concept you find it redundant like
what's your thoughts on this this thing
of a useful yeah you have to be careful
but I would say sure you don't want to
come to kind of I think it's always
helpful to step back step up look down
what you've been doing look around kind
of withdraw for a while and take that
reflective attitude I'll give that give
everything you're doing a kind of
reflective attitude oh yeah I think I'm
more in favor of it I would as a
mechanical kind of process I probably
would probably be a little skeptical
about it cool so before we close out do
you have any kind of final thoughts for
us James no but I do well I do it away
and that is make sure we I want to make
sure we all use this terrific crisis as
not as a way of looking forward beyond
it not just at the crisis itself or its
solution try to keep in mind the fact
that this is going to be terrible but
something worse is coming I think the
the environmental issues sort of racing
at us from the other end of the century
I really I I'm quite quite impressed
with how serious they are so I want to
say remember this is a terrific problem
terrific crisis but they
a bigger one coming prepare for it
that's a good note to leave on so I'll
make some closing announcements and
maybe you can hang on just for a couple
more minutes to kind of hear what we're
doing here at the store
James I think you quite like it but yeah
thank you so much for coming on my
friend we would love to have you back
another jam session like this or
whatever you like really so at the James
at the stove we have something called
the wisdom gym where we have sort of
ecology of practices where we're playing
the infinite game together we have a lot
of facilitators in the room right now so
I'll call in a few of them and maybe we
can just kind of talk about what you
have coming up Travis man are you still
in the room I am yeah so actually you
talked about this a little bit James
today but I have an event in the wisdom
gym called breaking the frame and it's
every Wednesday so tonight at 7:30 p.m.
Eastern and in this we do a relational
practice where we actually examine our
own relationship with our worldviews and
the ways that those have changed
throughout time and use the mechanisms
that led to changes in worldviews as a
jumping off point for maybe creating
some cognitive flexibility around the
way that we view the world right now so
I posted the link for the registration
in the jet I hope to see some of you
there great and Jessica you have a
relational exegesis event and you also
have a book club for the event funny
game if you can mention that yeah so I
run a kind of book club well you do not
have to have read the book beforehand we
read collaboratively and we have
comments kind of a little bit like
people so the drop in every week is
called relational exegesis tomorrow at
4:00 p.m. est or 1 p.m. PST and we're
doing James Baldwin's stranger in the
village we're also small so starting a
book club on fine and infinite games
which is of the same genre so we're
doing one section every week I've posted
a link to getting more information about
that in the chat and I will post that
link again but if you're interested and
you're confuse
just DME my name is Freya unzoom write
an AJ bond
you got a shame boot can't break through
tomorrow if you can become that forbid
yeah thanks Peter thanks Jim
Thursday's at 6:00 p.m. we do what we
call shame breakthrough boot camp which
is a very interactive session where we
try to get in touch with and feel into a
little bit of our shame and then discuss
some of the theory around how to work
with it and it's really it's a bit
intense it's a bit vulnerable but it's
really fun yeah we'll do two more coming
up that we're experimenting with Ariella
could you talk about the dangerous space
that's a we have this this weekend yeah
sure
this Saturday at noon Eastern Time me
and Peter are experimenting with a new
concept called the dangerous space it's
kind of like a contrast a safe space
idea which ideas we're gonna like talk
about a specific political current issue
like race or trans politics like
something that's controversial and we're
gonna we're gonna try to talk about it
in a way where the foster like
understanding and integration instead of
debate and ideological dominance great
I'm looking forward to that and then I'm
gonna put my boy
Nicholas on the spot he has something
called concept unfolding it's it's very
juicy if you can meet yourself Nick
thank you Peter for putting me on this
ball once again we actually haven't set
a date for the second concept unfolding
what it is a way of developing concepts
from speed concepts by running them
through a lens and then expanding the
limits of your language so join me
whenever Peter decides that I'm worthy
of giving a wisdom Jim I'll be happy to
play the game with you yes and for the
record I think you're very worthy of
that my friend so that being said check
out the the website the store that's CA
there's many events coming up and the
stoah is based off a gift economy we
view this as a gift for all of us to
freely use in this time of need if
you're inspired to provide a gift to the
store or any of our facilitators
directly
you can do so at the store dot see a
slash gift and if you want to continue
this conversation I would recommend
going to the game be coffeehouse
it's another zoom link you can just go
there and you can just you have some
more all right thank you everyone for
coming out today James do you want to
stay stay